<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">CivicAldermen_1552-3</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n="1"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>Bawdes
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>1552.3
				<lb/>Court of Common Council, [ournal I6 MT: CoL/CC[0[01[016
				<lb/>f 228
				<lb/>Ad Cur<ex>ia</ex> tent<ex>a</ex> in ext<ex>er</ex>ior<ex>i</ex> Cam<ex>er</ex>a Guihald<ex>e</ex> Ciui<ex>ta</ex>t<ex>is</ex> london<ex>ij</ex> xj die
				<lb/>lanuar<ex>ij</ex> A<ex>nn</ex>o R<ex>eani</ex> R<ex>e</ex>g<ex>is</ex> Edwardi sexti Sexto coram Georgio barne maiore
				<lb/>Ciui<ex>ta</ex>t<ex>is</ex> london<ex>ij</ex> loh<ex>ann</ex>e Gresham mil<ex>ite</ex> Rolando hyll milite Ric<ex>ar</ex>0o
			</p>
			<pb n="2"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>To thaldr<ex>em</ex>an
				<lb/>of the warde of
				<lb/>Bassieshawe/.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Bobbes mil<ex>ite</ex> Rob<ex>er</ex>to Broke s<ex>er</ex>uient<ex>e</ex> ad legem ac Recordato<ex>re</ex> eiusd<ex>e</ex>m
				<lb/>Ciui<ex>ta</ex>t<ex>is</ex> &amp; al<ex>ijs</ex> lustic<ex>arijs</ex> &amp;c. p<ex>r</ex>isonar<ex>ia</ex> infrascript<ex>a</ex> videl<ex>iee</ex>t Margareta
				<lb/>Bell ad barr<ex>a</ex> duct<ex>a</ex> ac de &amp; sup<ex>er</ex> p<ex>rese</ex>ntac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>em siue Ind<ex>i</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a<ex>en</ex>t<ex>u</ex>
				<lb/>v<ex>er</ex>sus ipsam sep<ex>ar</ex>atim in Cur<ex>ia</ex> wardemot<ex>e</ex> p<ex>r</ex>o do<ex>mi</ex>no Rege nup<ex>er</ex> fact<ex>um</ex>
				<lb/>siue p<ex>rese</ex>ntat<ex>u</ex> arrectat<ex>a</ex> pl<ex>a</ex>cit<ex>auit</ex> non culp<ex>a</ex>b<ex>i</ex>l<ex>e</ex> &amp; inde pos<ex>uit</ex> se ve<ex>nire</ex>
				<lb/>f<ex>a</ex>c<ex>ias</ex> sep<ex>ar</ex>atim Ideo ven<ex>it</ex> inde lur<ex>ata</ex> &amp;c. &amp; sup<ex>er</ex> quo , will<ex>el</ex>m<ex>u</ex>s
				<lb/>loh<ex>ann</ex>es] [ba(..)ld] ,Garrard Aldermannus &amp; loh<ex>ann</ex>es maynard
				<lb/>Tmercerus vic<ex>e</ex>co<ex>ites</ex> virtute cuiusdam p<ex>re</ex>cepti p<ex>er</ex> p<ex>re</ex>d<ex>ietos</ex> Maiorem &amp;
				<lb/>Recordato<ex>re</ex> eiusd<ex>e</ex>m Ciui<ex>ta</ex>t<ex>is</ex> eis inde dir<ex>e</ex>c<ex>i</ex>i retour<ex>n</ex>averunt quoddam
				<lb/>panell<ex>u</ex> lur<ex>atoru</ex>m e quibus xij videl<ex>iee</ex>t loh<ex>ann</ex>es 0wyn loh<ex>ann</ex>es Bokett
				<lb/>Thomas banester henr<ex>ieus</ex> Grover Rob<ex>er</ex>tus hardy Ed<ex>uara</ex>us Baye Thomas
				<lb/>Bukk Thomas Carter will<ex>el</ex>m<ex>us</ex> Ryxman Ric<ex>ara</ex>us ffarrand Thomas baker
				<lb/>&amp; brianus Calverley exact<ex>i</ex> comp<ex>ar</ex>uer<ex>un</ex>t &amp; lur<ex>ati</ex> &amp; on<ex>er</ex>at<ex>i</ex> fuer<ex>unt</ex> qui
				<lb/>dicunt sup<ex>er</ex> sacr<ex>aentu</ex>m suu<ex>m</ex> q<ex>u</ex>od p<ex>re</ex>d<ex>ieta</ex> [mabe] Margareta est culp<ex>a</ex>b<ex>ilis</ex>
				<lb/>modo &amp; forma p<ex>r</ex>out &amp;c. Id<ex>e</ex>o consid<ex>eratu</ex>m est p<ex>er</ex> cur<ex>ia</ex> q<ex>u</ex>od p<ex>re</ex>d<ex>ieta</ex>
				<lb/>Margareta ab hinc ad ostiu exterior<ex>e</ex> huius Aule reducat<ex>u</ex>r iuxta ritu<ex>m</ex>
				<lb/>&amp; morem inde vetust<ex>u</ex> in biga posit<ex>a</ex> liripipijs v<ex>er</ex>sicolor<ex>ihus</ex> ornat<ex>a</ex> &amp;
				<lb/>cu pelvino<ex>ru</ex>m pulsac<ex>i</ex>o<ex>n</ex>ibus tintinabul<ex>is</ex> ereis &amp; al<ex>ijs</ex> h<ex>uius</ex>modi ridicul<ex>is</ex>
				<lb/>ac strident<ex>i</ex>b<ex>us</ex> instrument<ex>is</ex> p<ex>er</ex> publica Ciui<ex>ta</ex>t<ex>is</ex> loca &amp; p<ex>re</ex>sertim p<ex>er</ex> fora
				<lb/>m<ex>er</ex>cator<ex>ia</ex> f<ex>a</ex>ctis int<ex>er</ex>im ib<ex>i</ex>d<ex>e</ex>m varijs p<ex>r</ex>oclam<ex>aeioni</ex>b<ex>us</ex> eius malef<ex>a</ex>c<ex>t</ex>a
				<lb/>transg<ex>ressiones</ex> &amp; offens<ex>iones</ex> pop<ex>u</ex>lo circu<ex>m</ex>stant<ex>i</ex> exponend<ex>is</ex> &amp; declarantibus
				<lb/>ad Algate vsq<ex>ue</ex> deducat<ex>u</ex>r &amp; ib<ex>i</ex>dem ad carcerem vnde ven<ex>it</ex> p<ex>r</ex>otinus
				<lb/>reducat<ex>u</ex>r/
				<lb/>. ..
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 247v
				<lb/>By the Mayre].
				<lb/>0n the kinge o<ex>u</ex>r sou<ex>er</ex>aigne lordes behalf we straightly charge &amp; comaunde
				<lb/>you that ye see &amp; cause A good &amp; substancyall doble watche to be kepte
				<lb/>w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in yo<ex>u</ex>r said [watche to be kepte] warde in the seu<ex>er</ex>all vygill<ex>es</ex> of saint
				<lb/>lohn Baptyst &amp; saint Peter thappostell next comyng of good, sadde, dyscrete
				<lb/>&amp; honest householders of the same warde well &amp; defencyblye, harnysed &amp;
				<lb/>weaponed as shall become theim] &amp; not of naked &amp; vnable p<ex>er</ex>sonnes as
				<lb/>heretofore hath bein sene] And the same watche to be kepte in good &amp; quyet
				<lb/>mano<ex>ur</ex> w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>out any mano<ex>ur</ex> of Lyght<ex>es</ex> lo<ex>u</ex>rnet<ex>es</ex> vysars or any kinde of
				<lb/>noyse or mynstallcie And the same watche to beginne at ix of the clock in
				<lb/>the evenyng of either of the said vygill<ex>es</ex>] and so to contynue in good ordre
			</p>
			<pb n="3"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>8 mynstrell<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>and Players/*
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>foreyn
				<lb/>Mynstrell<ex>es</ex>/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>terme for
				<lb/>Apprentic<ex>es</ex>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>vntyll iiij of the clock in the mornyng And so nyghtly after to contynue
				<lb/>yo<ex>ur</ex> said watche according to yo<ex>ur</ex> former p<ex>re</ex>cept lately to you dyrected
				<lb/>vntyll ye shall haue fro<ex>m</ex> vs otherwyse in comaundem<ex>en</ex>t/ ffaile ye not this to
				<lb/>doo as ye will aunswer for the contrarie at yo<ex>u</ex>r p<ex>er</ex>yll yoven at the Guyldehall
				<lb/>this xxijth of lune] I553
				<lb/>Blakwell
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>ff 253.6 T2March) (Common council)
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>fforasmuche as dyu<ex>er</ex>se &amp; menye forein mynstrell<ex>es</ex> fro<ex>m</ex> the lyb<ex>er</ex>ties &amp;
				<lb/>fredo<ex>m</ex>me of this Cytie of london haue of late &amp; yet doo as co<ex>m</ex>enly exercyse
				<lb/>vse &amp; practyse their said scyence of mynstralsie w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the same Cytie &amp;
				<lb/>the lyb<ex>er</ex>ties therof as though thei were free of the same Cytie not onely to
				<lb/>the great losse &amp; hindraunse of the gaines &amp; p<ex>r</ex>ofitt<ex>es</ex> of the poore [people
				<lb/>(..)] MMynstrell<ex>es</ex> being fremen of the same Cytie but also dyrectly in menie
				<lb/>point<ex>es</ex> contrarie to the good auncyent &amp; alowed Act<ex>es</ex> Lawes &amp; ordeina<ex>u</ex>nc<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>heretofore taken made &amp; establysshed w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the said Cytie conc<ex>er</ex>nyng the
				<lb/>said mynstrell<ex>es</ex> being free of the same Cytie[ wherby muche dysordre evill
				<lb/>Rule vyce &amp; synne dothe secretly springe growe &amp; dayly insue w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the
				<lb/>said Cytie &amp; the lyb<ex>er</ex>ties of the same] Be yt therfore enacted ordayned &amp;
				<lb/>establysshed by the lorde Maire Aldr<ex>em</ex>en &amp; co<ex>m</ex>ens in this p<ex>re</ex>sent co<ex>m</ex>en
				<lb/>counsaill assembled &amp; by the aucthorytie of the same that no man<ex>er</ex> of
				<lb/>p<ex>er</ex>son or p<ex>er</ex>sons co<ex>m</ex>enly exercysing or vsing the mysterie of mynstralcie
				<lb/>being A forein or foreins of what estate degree or condyc<ex>i</ex>on soeu<ex>er</ex> he or
				<lb/>thei be doo at eny tyme fro hensforward vse occupie or exercyse eny
				<lb/>mynstralsie singing or playing vpon eny Instrument or instrument<ex>es</ex> [shall]
				<lb/>in any , coen hall Taverne, Inne, Alehouse[s], or eny other lyke place or
				<lb/>plac<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in this Cytie &amp; lyb<ex>er</ex>ties therof vpon paine that eu<ex>er</ex>ie suche
				<lb/>[offendo<ex>ur</ex>] fforrein mynstrell after monyssyon to him gevin by the maister
				<lb/>or by the wardeins of the ffelowship of mynstrell<ex>es</ex> shall lose forfeite] And
				<lb/>paye for eu<ex>er</ex>ye tyme that he shalbe founde doing contrarie to this Acte iij
				<lb/>s. iiij d.] thone half therof to thuse of the poore infant<ex>es</ex> in cryst<ex>es</ex> hospytall
				<lb/>&amp; thother half to the co<ex>m</ex>en boxe of the same felowship[. Be yt also ordeined
				<lb/>&amp; enacted by the aucthorytie aforesaid that no p<ex>er</ex>son of the said mysterie
				<lb/>or ffelowship being A free man of the said Cytie &amp; occupying mynstralcie
				<lb/>shall fro hensforth haue or take to keape in his s<ex>er</ex>vyce at ones but onely
				<lb/>one app<ex>re</ex>ntyce to thentent that the same App<ex>re</ex>ntyce [to thentente that the
			</p>
			<pb n="4"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>for pleying in
				<lb/>open stret<ex>es</ex>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>8 Thomas
				<lb/>Hardinge
				<lb/>8 Ar/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>same app<ex>re</ex>ntyce] maye the better be aplyed lerned &amp; sett a woorke excepte
				<lb/>those p<ex>er</ex>sones of the sayd mysterie w<ex>hi</ex>ch be or haue bein m<ex>as</ex>t<ex>er</ex> or wardein
				<lb/>of the same to whom it shalbe leifull to haue take &amp; keape in his s<ex>er</ex>vyce at
				<lb/>once ij app<ex>re</ex>ntyces &amp; not aboue[. And yf eny p<ex>er</ex>son of the said mysterie
				<lb/>doo contrarie to this ordeina<ex>u</ex>nce he shall forfayte at eu<ex>er</ex>ye tyme so doyng
				<lb/>xl s.] to be applyed to thuse aforesaid] &amp; after monyc<ex>i</ex>on gevin to putt awaye
				<lb/>suche app<ex>re</ex>ntyce ,orels  to forfait x s. for eu<ex>er</ex>ye monethe [for] ,that he
				<lb/>shall  kepe[ng] [of] the same app<ex>re</ex>ntyce to be applyed as aforesaid] And
				<lb/>further be it ordeined &amp; enacted by the said aucthorytie that no mann<ex>er</ex> of
				<lb/>p<ex>er</ex>son or p<ex>er</ex>sones vsing or occupying playing vpon any Instrument or
				<lb/>Instrument<ex>es</ex>] doo fro hensforth playe vpon any man<ex>er</ex> of Instrument
				<lb/>w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the said Cytie or lyb<ex>er</ex>ties of the same in the open streat<ex>es</ex> Lanes or
				<lb/>Alleis therof fro or after .x. of the clock in the Evenyng vntyll .v. of the
				<lb/>clock in the mornyng vpon paine of forfaiture of .x. s. of Laufull money of
				<lb/>England for eu<ex>er</ex>ye tyme that he or thei shall so offende contrarie to the true
				<lb/>meanyng of this p<ex>re</ex>sent Acte to be imployed to thuse aforesaid [And after
				<lb/>monyc<ex>i</ex>on gevin to putt awaye suche app<ex>re</ex>ntyce to forfaite .x. s. eu<ex>er</ex>ye
				<lb/>monethe for keping of the same app<ex>re</ex>ntyce to be] l [applyed as aforesaid/
				<lb/>And further be yt ordeyned &amp; enacted by the said aucthorytie that no
				<lb/>mann<ex>er</ex> of p<ex>er</ex>son or p<ex>er</ex>sones vsing or occupying] All w<ex>hi</ex>ch forefaytures to
				<lb/>be recou<ex>er</ex>ed by acc<ex>i</ex>on of dett byll plaint or informac<ex>i</ex>on to be brought in
				<lb/>the name of the p<ex>re</ex>senter or p<ex>re</ex>sento<ex>ur</ex>s in the king<ex>es</ex> maiesties court holden
				<lb/>before the lorde Maire &amp; Aldr<ex>em</ex>en of the said Cytie for the tyme being in
				<lb/>the vtter Chamb<ex>er</ex> of the Guyldehall of the same Cytie in w<ex>hi</ex>ch acc<ex>i</ex>on no
				<lb/>wager of Lawe or essoyne for the defendaunt shalbe admytted or allowed/
				<lb/>P<ex>r</ex>ovyded alwayes that this p<ex>re</ex>sent Acte or eny thinge ther in conteyned
				<lb/>shall not extende or be p<ex>re</ex>iudyciall to the co<ex>m</ex>en wayt<ex>es</ex> of the said Cytie
				<lb/>in pleying or keping their accustumed watche as thei at their accustomed
				<lb/>tymes &amp; howres vse &amp; heretofore haue vsed the same eny thing afore rehersed
				<lb/>to the contrarie in eny wyse not w<ex>i</ex>thstanding] It<ex>e</ex>m forasmuche as dyu<ex>er</ex>se
				<lb/>&amp; menie Artyfyc<ex>er</ex>s &amp; handye craft<ex>es</ex> men as Tayllo<ex>u</ex>rs Showmakers &amp;
				<lb/>suche other leving the vse &amp; exercyse of their craft<ex>es</ex> &amp; manuall occupac<ex>i</ex>ons
				<lb/>&amp; geving theim self<ex>es</ex> holy to wandering abrode Ryott vyce &amp; Idlenes doo
				<lb/>co<ex>m</ex>enly vse nowe A dayes to singe song<ex>es</ex> called thre mens song<ex>es</ex> in the
				<lb/>Tavernes Alehouses Innes &amp; suche other plac<ex>es</ex> of this Cytie] &amp; also at
				<lb/>weading<ex>es</ex> &amp; other great feast<ex>es</ex> made w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the same Cytie to the great
				<lb/>Losse p<ex>re</ex>iudyce &amp; hindraunce of the said poore felowshop of the mynstrell<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>of the said Cytie] Be yt therfore also ordeined &amp; enacted by the aucthorytie
				<lb/>aforesaid that no man<ex>er</ex> of p<ex>er</ex>son or p<ex>er</ex>sons whether he or thei be free of
			</p>
			<pb n="5"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>8for daunsyng
				<lb/>scoles/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>the said Cytie or not free vsing to singe eny song<ex>es</ex> co<ex>m</ex>enly called thre mens
				<lb/>song<ex>es</ex> shall fro hensforth synge in or at any Taverne Inne Alehouse weding<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>ffeast<ex>es</ex> or eny other lyke place or plac<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the said Cytie or lyb<ex>er</ex>ties
				<lb/>therof eny man<ex>er</ex> of suche songe or song<ex>es</ex> (except the same be songe in A
				<lb/>coen playe or enterlude vpon paine of forfeiture by eu<ex>er</ex>ye suche p<ex>er</ex>son
				<lb/>&amp; p<ex>er</ex>sons after monyc<ex>i</ex>on to him or theim gevin of this p<ex>re</ex>sent Acte by the
				<lb/>Maist<ex>er</ex>s or wardeins of the said felowship for the tyme being for eu<ex>er</ex>ye
				<lb/>tyme that he or thei shalbe founde so doing contrarie to the p<ex>u</ex>rporte &amp;
				<lb/>trewe meanyng of this Acte iij s. iiij d. to be recou<ex>er</ex>ed &amp; imployed as ys
				<lb/>aforesaid P<ex>r</ex>ovyded also &amp; be it enacted &amp; by the aucthorytie aforesaid that
				<lb/>yt shall not be lefull to any mynstrell either , forein or freman or any other
				<lb/>p<ex>er</ex>son to keape or teache any sko[l[le of daunsing w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the said Cytie or
				<lb/>lyb<ex>er</ex>ties therof vpon paine to forfeite for eu<ex>er</ex>ye suche offence x li. the same
				<lb/>to be recou<ex>er</ex>ed &amp; imployed in suche sorte as before ys remembred/.
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>ff 254v. 57 TMarch)
				<lb/>. ..
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m for soundrie verie good necessarie &amp; godly consyderac<ex>i</ex>ons &amp; causes
				<lb/>esp<ex>e</ex>cially moving the lorde Maire Aldr<ex>em</ex>en &amp; co<ex>m</ex>ens in this p<ex>re</ex>sent co<ex>m</ex>en
				<lb/>counsaill assembled yt was ordeyned enacted &amp; establysshed by the same
				<lb/>that no man<ex>er</ex> of p<ex>er</ex>son or p<ex>er</ex>sones nowe being or that herafter shalbe free
				<lb/>of the Cytie of london or eny other what soeu<ex>er</ex> m<ex>er</ex>chauntt w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the
				<lb/>same Cytie or the lyb<ex>er</ex>ties ther of shall fro hensforth p<ex>er</ex>mytt or suffre
				<lb/>eny man<ex>er</ex> of enterlude or co<ex>m</ex>en playe to be had made or played w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in
				<lb/>eny p<ex>ar</ex>te of his or their howse or howses yarde Gardein or backsyde either
				<lb/>vpon the Sabott daye or vpon eny other what soeu<ex>er</ex> festyvall or holy daye
				<lb/>co<ex>m</ex>maunded by the churche Before the houre of thre of the clock in the
				<lb/>afternone of eu<ex>er</ex>ye suche daye vpon paine of losing &amp; forfeiture of .xl. s.
				<lb/>for eu<ex>er</ex>ye suche defalte nor that eny suche p<ex>er</ex>son or p<ex>er</ex>sones being free or
				<lb/>that herafter shalbe free or inh<ex>a</ex>bite w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in eny p<ex>ar</ex>te of the said Cytie or the
				<lb/>lyb<ex>er</ex>ties ther of shall p<ex>er</ex>mytt or suffre at eny tyme herafter eny nu<ex>m</ex>bre of
				<lb/>people to congregate &amp; gather togyther w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in his or their said house or
				<lb/>houses yarde gardein or baksyde or w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in eny p<ex>ar</ex>te of eny of the same
				<lb/>seu<ex>er</ex>all plac<ex>es</ex> vpon eny of the dayes aboue recyted before the houre aforesaid
				<lb/>to the intent there to here or see eny suche enterlude or co<ex>m</ex>en playe made
				<lb/>or played vpon the paine &amp; forfeiture aboue remembred] All w<ex>hi</ex>ch paines
				<lb/>&amp; forfaitures vpon the recou<ex>er</ex>ye of the same shalbe devyded into thre
				<lb/>equall p<ex>ar</ex>tes &amp; imployed to thuses herunder wryten] That ys to saye to the
				<lb/>vse of the Maire &amp; co<ex>m</ex>i<ex>n</ex>altie &amp; Cytezens of the said Cytie xiij s. iiij d. to
			</p>
			<pb n="6"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>WTo thaldr<ex>em</ex>an
				<lb/>of the warde of
				<lb/>Colmanstrete/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>the vse of the poore in the house of the poore in west smythfeld of the said
				<lb/>Cytie xiij s. iiij d.] &amp; to the vse of the p<ex>re</ex>sent<ex>er</ex> of eu<ex>er</ex>ye suche defalte &amp;
				<lb/>offence xiij s. iiij d.] And shalbe recou<ex>er</ex>ed by the waye of Acc<ex>i</ex>on of dett to
				<lb/>be co<ex>m</ex>menced in the name of the Chamb<ex>er</ex>lein of the said Cytie for the
				<lb/>tyme being by bill orygynall in o<ex>u</ex>r sou<ex>er</ex>aigne Lord [(..)] the [0ue] king<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>court holden in the vtt<ex>er</ex> ] Chamber of the Guyldhall of the said Cytie before
				<lb/>the lorde Maire &amp; Aldr<ex>em</ex>en of the same Cytie for the tyme being in w<ex>hi</ex>ch
				<lb/>Acc<ex>i</ex>on no wager of Lawe or esson for the defendaunt shalbe admytted or
				<lb/>allowed/
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 2GT(T August) (Common council)
				<lb/>...
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m at this court there was A xvene &amp; di.] lovingly &amp; frely geven &amp; graunted
				<lb/>by the lorde Maire Aldr<ex>em</ex>en &amp; co<ex>m</ex>ens at the same court assembled &amp; by
				<lb/>the aucthorytie of the same toward<ex>es</ex> the charg<ex>es</ex> that the Cytie nowe must
				<lb/>beare &amp; be at for the accustumed p<ex>re</ex>sent of A Ml mark<ex>es</ex> to be geven to
				<lb/>our most gracyous &amp; most benygne sou<ex>er</ex>aigne Ladie 0uene Marie at her
				<lb/>highnes Coronac<ex>i</ex>on And for the try<ex>m</ex>myng &amp; garnysshing of the Gat<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>Condytt<ex>es</ex> &amp; streat<ex>es</ex> of this Cytie at her g<ex>r</ex>ac<ex>es</ex> co<ex>m</ex>myng thurrough the
				<lb/>same] the same xvne &amp; di.] to be taxed levyed &amp; gathered of the Cytezens
				<lb/>&amp; inh<ex>a</ex>bitaunt<ex>es</ex> of this Cytie in suche wyse &amp; sorte as other xvnes are
				<lb/>co<ex>m</ex>enly taxed levyed &amp; gathered/.
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>ff 262.2v
				<lb/>. ..
				<lb/>By the Maire/
				<lb/>0n the behalf of o<ex>u</ex>r most gracyous &amp; most benygne sou<ex>er</ex>aign Ladie Marie
				<lb/>by the grace of god 0uene of England ffraunce &amp; Treland defender of the
				<lb/>faythe &amp; of the churche of England &amp; also of Treland in erthe the sup<ex>re</ex>me
				<lb/>hed] we doo straightly charge &amp; co<ex>m</ex>maunde you that you or yo<ex>ur</ex> deputie
				<lb/>i<ex>m</ex>medyatly vpon the receypte &amp; sight herof all other maters &amp; execuses sett
				<lb/>ap<ex>ar</ex>te doo cause all the p<ex>er</ex>sones vycars &amp; curat<ex>es</ex> of the seu<ex>er</ex>all p<ex>ar</ex>yshe or
				<lb/>collegyall churches w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in yo<ex>ur</ex> said warde w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>out delaye p<ex>er</ex>sonallye to
				<lb/>appere before you] And that ye lyke wyse doo gyve then &amp; there vnto theim
			</p>
			<pb n="7"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>Coke
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>8Mynstrell<ex>es</ex> &amp;
				<lb/>int<ex>er</ex>ludes/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>&amp; eu<ex>er</ex>ye of theim streight charge &amp; comaundement on the behalf of o<ex>u</ex>r said
				<lb/>sou<ex>er</ex>aigne Ladie the 0uene that thei or any of theim at eny tyme herafter
				<lb/>doo not preache or reade openly nor suffre to be redde or p<ex>re</ex>chead by any
				<lb/>other man any mann<ex>er</ex> of Sermo<ex>m</ex> or lecture in any churches chappell<ex>es</ex> or
				<lb/>other place or plac<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in yo<ex>u</ex>r said warde vntyll suche tyme as , thei shalbe
				<lb/>further ] adu<ex>er</ex>tesed of her grac<ex>es</ex> pleasure in this behalf] And also that ye doo
				<lb/>straightly admonyshe &amp; charge eu<ex>er</ex>ye of theim the said p<ex>ar</ex>sons vycars &amp;
				<lb/>Curat<ex>es</ex> that thei &amp; eu<ex>er</ex>ye of theim doo plainly &amp; dystinctly fro<ex>m</ex> hensforthe
				<lb/>reade openly in eu<ex>er</ex>ye of their said churches vpon eu<ex>er</ex>ye sonndaye the Acte
				<lb/>of p<ex>ar</ex>lyament conc<ex>er</ex>nyng vnlaufull assemblies &amp; rebellyon made in the thirde 
				<lb/>yere of the Reigne of o<ex>ur</ex> late sou<ex>er</ex>aigne lorde kinge Edwarde the vjth during
				<lb/>the said tyme] And furthermore that ye the said Aldr<ex>em</ex>an doo not p<ex>er</ex>mytt
				<lb/>or suffre any co<ex>m</ex>en playes or enterlud<ex>es</ex> to be made or played at eny tyme
				<lb/>herafter w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in any man<ex>er</ex> of place or plac<ex>es</ex> of yo<ex>u</ex>r said warde] ffayle ye not
				<lb/>thus to doo as ye will aunswer for the contrarie at yo<ex>ur</ex> vttermost p<ex>er</ex>yll<ex>es</ex> 
				<lb/>yoven at the Guyldehall the xvjth of this p<ex>re</ex>sent August in the first yere of
				<lb/>the Reigne of o<ex>u</ex>r said sou<ex>er</ex>aigne Ladie 0uene Marie[.
				<lb/>Blakwell
				<lb/>. .  e
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Court of Aldermen, Repertory 13(1) MT: CoL/CA[0i[o1[014
				<lb/>f 26v  TMarch)
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>It<ex>e</ex>m it was orderyd &amp; adiuged by the hole co<ex>u</ex>rte that nich<ex>ol</ex>as Coke one
				<lb/>of the bedell<ex>es</ex> of the pore laufully convycted here this day by good &amp;
				<lb/>suffycient wytnesses of the fylthye cryme &amp; offence of fornycac<ex>i</ex>on by hym
				<lb/>comytted &amp; done shall eyther laufully mary w<ex>i</ex>th the p<ex>er</ex>son so by hym
				<lb/>vyciated orel<ex>es</ex> to morowe Ryde about the Cytie in a Carte w<ex>i</ex>th a ray hode
				<lb/>vpon his hed &amp; a whyte rod in his hand &amp; basons &amp; pa<ex>n</ex>nes Rynginge
				<lb/>before hym accordynge to the auncyent lawes of this Cytie in suche case
				<lb/>ordeyned &amp; p<ex>r</ex>ovyded/
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 28T7March)
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>It<ex>e</ex>m it was agreid that the sundry act<ex>es</ex> of co<ex>m</ex>en counseyll lately made &amp;
				<lb/>establyshed conc<ex>er</ex>nyng mynstrell<ex>es</ex> &amp; enterludes shalbe p<ex>r</ex>oclaymed to
				<lb/>morowe/
			</p>
			<pb n="8"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>co<ex>m</ex>en
				<lb/>harlott<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>Intr<ex>atur</ex>5
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>Intr<ex>atur</ex>
				<lb/>obsequiu de
				<lb/>lez m<ex>er</ex>chaunt<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>straung<ex>er</ex>s
				<lb/>tempo<ex>r</ex>e
				<lb/>coronac<ex>ionis</ex>
				<lb/>Reg<ex>in</ex>e/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f A2 .(4 May)
				<lb/>Tt<ex>e</ex>m it was ordered and adiudged that lohn chamb<ex>er</ex>leyne pavyo<ex>u</ex>r and
				<lb/>Elysabeth Maltham who of theire owne co<ex>n</ex>fessyon here openly made this
				<lb/>Bay ar guyltie of the Betestable vice and cryme of lechery betwyne theyme
				<lb/>dyuers and meny tymes co<ex>m</ex>mytted shall to morowe according to the
				<lb/>Auncye<ex>n</ex>te lawe and vsage of this cytie be caryede thoroughe the markett
				<lb/>plac<ex>es</ex> and open stret<ex>es</ex> of the said Cytie in a Carte w<ex>i</ex>th Ray hod<ex>es</ex> vpo<ex>n</ex>
				<lb/>theire head<ex>es</ex> whyte Rod<ex>es</ex> in theire hand<ex>es</ex> and basons and pannes of brasse
				<lb/>Ringing before theyme and then to be expelled owte of the sam Cytie not
				<lb/>to Retorne agayne in to the same excepte they shall first be lycencede by
				<lb/>the Lorde Mayer of the same Cytye or some of his bretheren thaldermen
				<lb/>for the tyme beinge so to do vpo<ex>n</ex> payne of goyng to the pyllorye/
				<lb/>...
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 40 T2May) (Parish clerks ordinances)
				<lb/>...
				<lb/>e And that no forreyn Clerk or singing ma<ex>n</ex>ne not being freman of the Cytie
				<lb/>of London shall take vpon hym any service or Clerkeshipp<ex>e</ex> w<ex>i</ex>thin the saide
				<lb/>Cytie or Lib<ex>er</ex>ties of the same before he have p<ex>re</ex>sentyd hym<ex>m</ex>e self to the
				<lb/>masters and warde<ex>i</ex>ns of the saiede company and ffelowshipp of p<ex>ar</ex>ishe
				<lb/>Clerk<ex>es</ex> and to pay for his admyssyon iij s. iiij d. vpon payne of hyme that
				<lb/>shall doe the contrarie xx s. to be levied to the vses aforesaid...
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 60vT27/uly)
				<lb/>...
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m the Corte for certayne good co<ex>n</ex>siderac<ex>i</ex>ons theyme esp<ex>ee</ex>iallye movynge
				<lb/>did lycence the flore<ex>n</ex>tynes and other marchauntes Straungers resina<ex>u</ex>nte
				<lb/>at this p<ex>rese</ex>nte w<ex>i</ex>thin this Cytie not onely to attende vpon the 0uenes
				<lb/>Ma<ex>ies</ex>ty on horseback at her highenes co<ex>m</ex>mynge thorough the Cytie to
				<lb/>her coronac<ex>i</ex>on but also to erecte and make a pagye<ex>n</ex>te the same tyme at
				<lb/>ledenhall/
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<pb n="9"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>Intrat<ex>ur</ex>
				<lb/>ye maier and
				<lb/>Aldr<ex>em</ex>en to
				<lb/>mete the
				<lb/>0uenes
				<lb/>highenes
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>p<ex>ar</ex>ishe clerk<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>singinge men
				<lb/>and mynstrell<ex>es</ex>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>The companies
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>silk<ex>es</ex> and other
				<lb/>Ryche clothes
				<lb/>to be hanged
				<lb/>owte/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>p<ex>ar</ex>ishe clerk<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>&amp; mynstrell<ex>es</ex>
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>p<ex>re</ex>cept<ex>es</ex> for ye
				<lb/>xvne &amp; di.
				<lb/>lately graunted
				<lb/>&amp;c.]
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 70v T2A<ex>u</ex>gust)
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>At this Corte it is agreed that my Lorde Mayer and his b[e]rethern shall to
				<lb/>morowe in the after none ryde to mete the 0uenes maiestie at the barres
				<lb/>w<ex>i</ex>thowte Algate and there takynge theire plac<ex>es</ex> by the appoynteme<ex>n</ex>te of
				<lb/>the harrold of armes to ryde furthe before her hyghenes as farr as the harrold
				<lb/>shall appoynte theym/
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m the p<ex>ar</ex>ishe Clerk<ex>es</ex> and the wardens of the mynstrell<ex>es</ex> were co<ex>m</ex>maunded
				<lb/>to be in a redynes w<ex>i</ex>th singinge men for the Receyving of the 0uenes grace
				<lb/>and they to co<ex>n</ex>sult w<ex>i</ex>th theire companie therefore] by the wey from Algate
				<lb/>to Leaden hall gracious strete ffanchurche strete marte Lane and Towerstrete
				<lb/>at suche plac<ex>es</ex> as they shall think mete and certefy my Lorde maior thereof
				<lb/>this after none and therevpon my Lorde mayer and c<ex>er</ex>tayne of my M<ex>as</ex>tres
				<lb/>thaldermen did agre to vyewe the same plac<ex>es</ex> theym selves this after none/
				<lb/>It<ex>e</ex>m all the companies of Craft<ex>es</ex> to p<ex>re</ex>payre Reyll<ex>es</ex> for theire standing<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>and they to stande in theire lyu<ex>er</ex>ies to Receyve her grace begynnynge w<ex>i</ex>th
				<lb/>the meaneste companies firste at the well w<ex>i</ex>th ij buckett<ex>es</ex> w<ex>i</ex>thyn Algate
				<lb/>and so eche companie in order after other to leaden hall &amp;c. as they be of
				<lb/>Auncye<ex>n</ex>tie so farre as they may stretche/
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m it was ordered that my M<ex>aist</ex>res thaldermen thoroughe whose wardes
				<lb/>the 0uenes highenes shall passe to the Tower shall geve warnynge to
				<lb/>thinh<ex>a</ex>bitaunt<ex>es</ex> of the same wardes to hange oute all suche ryche clothes of
				<lb/>Aras clothe of Sylver and of goold as they haue or can<ex>m</ex>e geate oute at theire
				<lb/>wyndowses and stall<ex>es</ex> at the 0uenes highenes co<ex>m</ex>mynge hether to morowe
				<lb/>to the Tower/
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m it was agreed that my Lorde Mayer M<ex>r</ex> Bowes M<ex>r</ex> ludde M<ex>r</ex> wodrof
				<lb/>M<ex>r</ex> ofeley and M<ex>r</ex> wyther shall this after none appoynte the plac<ex>es</ex> and stag<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>betweyne Algate and the Tower where the mynstrell<ex>es</ex> and p<ex>ar</ex>ishe clerk<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>shall stonde at the 0uenes highenes co<ex>m</ex>mynge thether/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>ff 74v. 57 (20 August)
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m it was ordered and agreed that precept<ex>es</ex> shalbe made furthe to eu<ex>er</ex>y
				<lb/>of my m<ex>ast</ex>res thaldermen withe spede for the assesseme<ex>n</ex>te and collecc<ex>i</ex>on
				<lb/>of the xvne and an half that is lately graunted by the co<ex>m</ex>en co<ex>u</ex>nseyll to
				<lb/>the quenes ma<ex>ies</ex>ties at her grac<ex>es</ex> coronac<ex>i</ex>on and to wardes the Cyties
				<lb/>charg<ex>es</ex> to be susteyned by occasyon of the same abowte the garnyshing of
			</p>
			<pb n="10"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>the condytt<ex>es</ex> the crosse in cheape and otherwyse at her grac<ex>es</ex> passinge
				<lb/>thorowghe the Cytie to the same And it was also agreed and ordered that
				<lb/>the p<ex>er</ex>sons herevnder named should take the paynes and charge to se and
				<lb/>cause all the said conditt<ex>es</ex> and other plac<ex>es</ex> hereafter named to be very comely
				<lb/>and freshely trymmed and garnyshed in suche sorte as they were ordered
				<lb/>and decked at the tyme of the Coronac<ex>i</ex>on of our late sou<ex>er</ex>einge Lorde
				<lb/>Tynge Edward the sixthe or better if they can ffirste ffanchurche is lefte to
				<lb/>the orderinge and trim<ex>m</ex>ynge of the merchaunt<ex>es</ex> Straungers dwellinge by
				<lb/>the same who haue alreadye p<ex>r</ex>omysed to see it very well done and for the
				<lb/>condite in Cornehill there ar appoynted Philipp Gunter and Thomas Hunt
				<lb/>Skynners and ph<ex>i</ex>lipp Bolde clotheworker ffor
				<lb/>The greate Condyte in Cheape/
				<lb/>Galfr<ex>ia</ex>us walkeden Skynn<ex>er</ex> Clemens Cornewall Tremongre (blank) ffox
				<lb/>goldesmythe et george Tadlowe Habberdassher/
				<lb/>ffor the Standard in cheape/
				<lb/>Roland heywerde clotheworker Clemens newce[ m<ex>er</ex>cer Rob<ex>er</ex>t<ex>us</ex> 0sington
				<lb/>letherseller et Thomas Lun groc<ex>er</ex>
				<lb/>ffor the crose in cheape/
				<lb/>Ric<ex>araus</ex> ffowlk<ex>es</ex> clotheworker Thomas pickett groc<ex>er</ex> Rob<ex>er</ex>t<ex>us</ex> wigge
				<lb/>aur<ex>i</ex>fab<ex>er</ex> et Alex<ex>an</ex>d<ex>er</ex> avenon Tremonger[
				<lb/>ffor the lytle condite in cheape/
				<lb/>Ric<ex>araus</ex> Buckelond hab<ex>er</ex>d<ex>asher</ex> Thomas Raynes aur<ex>i</ex>f<ex>a</ex>b<ex>er</ex> loh<ex>ann</ex>es Langeley
				<lb/>et loh<ex>ann</ex>es Clerk aur<ex>i</ex>f<ex>a</ex>b<ex>er</ex>/
				<lb/>ffor Ludgate/
				<lb/>Ric<ex>araus</ex> Aleyn hab<ex>er</ex>d<ex>asher</ex> henr<ex>ieus</ex> moyler Clotheworker chr<ex>is</ex>tofer harebotell
				<lb/>hab<ex>er</ex>d<ex>asher</ex> et loh<ex>ann</ex>es Lacye clotheworker/
				<lb/>for the condyte in flete strete/
				<lb/>Thomas barthelett Stacyon<ex>er</ex> et Edward whitechurche] loh<ex>ann</ex>es Hulson
				<lb/>Scryven<ex>er</ex> et Thomas Sponer au[(.)]r<ex>ila</ex>b<ex>er</ex>//
				<lb/>ffor Temple Barre/
				<lb/>will<ex>el</ex>mus lames Simon ponder loh<ex>ann</ex>es horneby et loh<ex>ann</ex>es Leyceter/
				<lb/>Cuteler
			</p>
			<pb n="11"/>
			<p>
				<lb/>London and
				<lb/>the Cytizens to
				<lb/>Attend vpon
				<lb/>the 0uenes
				<lb/>highenes &amp;c./
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>8Bedforde a
				<lb/>co<ex>m</ex>en
				<lb/>Avouter<ex>e</ex>r//
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>And it was also ordered that they shalbe all warned to be here the nexte corte
				<lb/>Bay to receyve informac<ex>i</ex>on howe they shall vse theym selves [t]herein
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>f 70..(26 September)
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>At this Corte it was ordered and agreyd that all the co<ex>m</ex>panies of this Cytie
				<lb/>that co<ex>m</ex>enly doe Attend vpon the Lorde mayer Att eu<ex>er</ex>y co<ex>m</ex>en Assemble
				<lb/>shalbe warned furthew<ex>i</ex>th to awayte vpon the 0uenes highenes vpon the
				<lb/>Ryver of Theamis to morwe in the After none from westm<ex>ins</ex>t<ex>er</ex> to the Tower
				<lb/>in theire comely and good Aparell and in barg<ex>es</ex> or botes well garnysshed
				<lb/>and trymmed w<ex>i</ex>th flagg<ex>es</ex> ba<ex>n</ex>ners and mynstralcye or suche other orname<ex>n</ex>t<ex>es</ex>
				<lb/>as they shall think mete/
			</p>
			<p>
				<lb/>ff 80. 80v
				<lb/>. . .
				<lb/>lt<ex>e</ex>m it was adiudged and agreyd that Edwarde bedforde Carman lyvinge in
				<lb/>Advowtery w<ex>i</ex>th a s<ex>e</ex>co<ex>n</ex>de wyf whome he hathe maried knoweng his firste
				<lb/>wyf to be levinge whereof he was this Bay of his owne Confession here
				<lb/>playnely convycte shall tomorowe according to tha<ex>u</ex>ncie<ex>n</ex>te lawes and
				<lb/>laudable customes of this Cytie be caryed aboute] ] And thoroughe the
				<lb/>open stret<ex>es</ex> and markett places of the same Cytie in a carte w<ex>i</ex>th a Ray
				<lb/>hode vpon his head and a whyte Rod in his hand and basons and pan<ex>n</ex>es
				<lb/>Ringinge before hym and then be Reco<ex>m</ex>mytted to warde till my Lorde
				<lb/>Maiers pleasure shalbe knowen for his Belyu<ex>er</ex>ye And it was also orderyd
				<lb/>that his said s<ex>e</ex>co<ex>n</ex>de wyf should furthw<ex>i</ex>th delyu<ex>er</ex> to his said firste wyf all
				<lb/>suche Rayme<ex>n</ex>te and other thing<ex>es</ex> as she then had of his or of the same
				<lb/>his firste wyfes/
				<lb/>. . .
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>